Guide to the Fred J. Buenzle papers M1983
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Fred J. Buenzle papers
1870s-1986
M1983
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
6.0 Linear feet (5 boxes)
Manuscripts, scrapbooks, correspondence and photographs from Fred J. Buenzle (1872-1946), Chief Yeoman of the United States Navy.
Buenzle, Fred J.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
Frederick John Buenzle (1872-1946) enlisted in the United States Navy at the age of sixteen, and chronicled the transition of the Navy's fleet from the sailing ships of the 19th century to steam-powered steel boats and the accompanying changes in sailors' duties and culture. Training aboard the U.S.S. Portsmouth, Buenzle traveled around the Caribbean before assuming the job of stenographer, eventually working his way up to Chief Yeoman. Buenzle took shorthand for Rear Admiral William Sampson, acting Secretary of the Navy William McAdoo and even on occasion Theodore Roosevelt. He also ran the Yeoman School in Newport, Rhode Island for a time.
Buenzle was founder and editor of the first magazine for enlisted sailors, "The Bluejacket," also the name of his 1939 memoir. While there are no copies of the newsletter in the collection, other shipboard newsletters are present. Buenzle also successfully filed a lawsuit fighting discrimination against uniformed servicemen.
Buenzle was stenographer for the Court of Inquiry concerning the sinking of the U.S.S. Maine in 1898 (for which Sampson was Chief), and subsequently participated in the Spanish-American War aboard the U.S.S. New York. There are numerous photographs and documents concerning Cuba and the war.
After retiring in 1912 due to hearing loss, Buenzle moved around the country trying his hand at various occupations before settling in Los Gatos at his ranch, known as "Snug Harbor," where he farmed, built model ships and continued to write until his death in 1946.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in July 2013.
United States. Navy.; Military history; Naval history; Spanish-American War, 1898.
- Newport Navalog biographical profile, 1967-07 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Apprenticeship Memories Revived -or- 4 Years in the U.S.N." bound manuscript, 1889-1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  An account of Buenzle's training aboard the Portsmouth in the Caribbean. Includes souvenir postcards of Jamaica, two large albumen prints of St. Thomas, and newspaper clippings from the Newport Sentinel of letters Buenzle wrote to the paper.
- "That Mutiny of Ours" bound typescript, c.1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  A narrative of the 1842 alleged mutiny aboard the U.S.S. Somers in which three sailors were hanged without a legal trial.
- "One Hundred Years Ago" typescript re: U.S.S. Somers incident, 1942-09-10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bluejacket: An Autobiography, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Reprint by the Naval Institute Press in their Classics of Naval Literature series. Originally published by W.W. Norton in 1939.
- "Old Navy Men" typescript, c. 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- reprints, U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 1940, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Here Comes A Sailor" Chapter XIII excerpt about his brief interaction with future King George V of England (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Naval Casualties in Peacetime" typescript [published copy in scrapbook] (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Three Days in the Rice Fields of China" manuscript (Box 1, Folder 10)
  After five years of service, in 1893 Buenzle left the Navy and lived in Shanghai. He became an officer in the Chinese military during the Sino-Japanese War, and "Three Days..." is a brief account of this experience.
- untitled speech transcript, U.S. Veterans' Home, Napa, with clipping about event, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- small notebook with addresses and accounts; small unidentified Chinese book with illustrations (Box 2, Folder 1)
- correspondence to King George V with form reply from King's Personal Secretary, 1935-09 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- correspondence re: Somers incident manuscript, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- scrapbook of approximately 80 silver gelatin prints including images of Naval training in Guantanamo Bay and other images in and around Havana, Cuba, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This scrapbook has been digitized by Stanford and is available for research.
- correspondence re: Spanish-American War with souvenir pieces of flag removed from Spanish vessel, 1940-02-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- bulletins, correspondence, memoranda and notes re: U.S.S. New York and Spanish-American War, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Field notes, "order of battle" memoranda, William T. Sampson communication, and other documents.
- miscellaneous Navy correspondence, notes and other documents, including Buenzle's enlistment record, 1894-1912 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- The Pelican, U.S.S. Louisiana newsletter, 1906-07 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Williwa, U.S.S. Pybus newsletters [8], 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- notes re: U.S.S. Portsmouth (Box 2, Folder 10)
- handwritten excerpt of review of Bluejacket, 1944-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- unidentified Chinese manuscript- 3 leaves, c.1890s (Box 2, Folder 12)
- photographs (Box 2, Folder 13, Folder 14)
- scrapbook of several hundred annotated silver prints, c.1880-1939 (Box 4, Folders 1-6, Box 5, Box 3, Folders 1-7)
  Large scrapbook with decorated wooden cover, featuring the Buenzle family and residences in Newport, Rhode Island, Los Gatos, California, and elsewhere, as well as newspaper clippings of articles by or about Buenzle (many with no source or date). Boxes 3 and 4 contain loose pages, and Box 5 contains the enclosure.